<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://katielf.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://katielf.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-01-27T22:58:51+00:00</updated><id>https://katielf.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Katie L. Friese</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Next Steps</title><link href="https://katielf.github.io/blog/2026/Next-Steps/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Next Steps"/><published>2026-01-18T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-18T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://katielf.github.io/blog/2026/Next-Steps</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://katielf.github.io/blog/2026/Next-Steps/"><![CDATA[<p>Greetings y’all,</p> <p>This posts bares as my record for what I hope to accomplish in the next few months.</p> <h2 id="current-career-situation">Current career situation</h2> <p>First off, back in August of 2025 I got a part time job that I loved. The team was amazing, I was learning new things all the time, and it was an amazing time for me. Then in December of that same year I got laid off by that company. It is a seasonal business and they were trying to expand but it didn’t end up working out this season.</p> <p>I had mentally gotten settled in that company and was actually starting to build up my savings again before the layoff hit so this was quite the mental hit for me. This combined with the current job market and my experiences trying to get hired have pushed me in a new direction.</p> <h2 id="what-fits-the-bill">What fits the bill?</h2> <p>It’s time to learn some new skills that can give me “physical” projects to showcase my skills. You can’t do that with people or organizational skills, but you can do that with coding.</p> <p>When I first got introduced to coding in University, it both intrigued me and frustrated me. It was fantastic that I got immediate feedback (whether the code worked or not) but I didn’t have the vocabulary to find my answers online. So after learning the basics of HTML, CSS, R, and Python, I moved on. While I enjoyed it I didn’t see how it could be useful.</p> <h2 id="next-steps">Next steps</h2> <p>After dating my boyfriend for a few years now and especially with the AWS outage that happened a few months ago, I see how coding and understanding the digital architecture is essential with the current day and age, even with AI takeing over the low level tasks. With learning these skills also came the perk of creating projects like a full-time minecraft server for my family, a Network-Attached Storage for all of my files (so they don’t get scrapped by AI), and making a personal website that fulfills my needs and interests.</p> <p>So, where does that leave me now? With the little savings I had built up I decided to enroll in the boot.dev course to teach me the basics of where I need to go. While I could brute force it by googling everything incessantly, I lack the language to be able to ask what I’m looking for. And on the plus side, it is waaayyyy cheaper then a lot of other “coding bootcamps”. It also has a learning system that works well for my, number go up. I get a streak for everyday I learn and xp for every lesson I complete, number go up = Katie’s brain likes to do it.</p> <p>With my current pace, I should finish up with the course by July or August of this year. By then I’ll have some projects done through the course and hopefully have a few more of my own. Then I can switch over my job hunt to hopefully something more long term then what I’ve been getting currently.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="update"/><category term="coding,"/><category term="baking"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[an update about what is going on for me career and skill wise]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sourdough tips and tricks</title><link href="https://katielf.github.io/blog/2025/Sourdough-tips-and-tricks/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sourdough tips and tricks"/><published>2025-04-10T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-10T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://katielf.github.io/blog/2025/Sourdough-tips-and-tricks</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://katielf.github.io/blog/2025/Sourdough-tips-and-tricks/"><![CDATA[<p>This is for a few friends at the DANCE lab that are just getting started in their sourdough adventure and needed a few starting tips.</p> <h1 id="introduction-to-fermentation">Introduction to ~fermentation~</h1> <p>Welcome to the amazing world of fermentation! That’s right! You have a bunch of lovely bacteria and wild yeasts that will help you make fantastic sourdough bread, rolls, and treats galore.</p> <p>For a more technical definition, a sourdough starter is a leavening agent in baking. It has it’s own quirks just like regular yeast or baking soda. Because it’s technically a living thing, it tends to get more picky with what it eats and grows in. But what it does eat it turns into carbon dioxide which is the rising agent for baking. Sourdough starters have been used for thousands if not hundreds of thousands of years. Old starters have been found as far back as ancient egypt in 3700 BCE but it’s likely that fermentation practices started even further back (according to the Encyclopedia of Food Microbiology, 2nd edition, pg. 309) Only once baker’s yeast started to become commercially available as a by product of the beer business (roughly 1871) did sourdough practices started to die off.</p> <p><strong>It should be in glass most of the time</strong> (all plastic is permeable in some way or another) <strong>but should be given the ability to breath.</strong> My favorite method is to put it in a glass mason jar and secure the top with a towel and a rubber band.</p> <p>PICTURE HERE OF MY BEAUTIFUL BABY BOY STERLING</p> <p>Just like with any leaving thing you need to feed it. But, like a cat, it doesn’t need to be super consistent. If you’re not planning on using it anytime soon, feed it and pop it in the fridge for a few weeks. Starter is surprisingly resilient and will usually spring back after a few feedings outside of the fridge.</p> <p>But what should you feed this wonderful conglomerate? <strong>A typical feeding as measured in grams (oh yeah, a scale will be your best friend in sourdough baking) is 1 part flour, 1 part water, and a bit of starter.</strong> How fast it ferments depends on how much starter you add, the ambient temperature, what minerals are in your water, etc. etc.</p> <p>If you forget to feed your starter one day or leave it in the fridge to lay dormant for a while, it will probably develop a blackish water floating on top of your starter. FEAR NOT! That’s actually the sign of a healthy starter. It’s getting rid of stuff it doesn’t need as it lies sleeping. Just dump off the liquid and feed your starter as normal. It might need a little more water to get the consistency right but it doesn’t matter terribly.</p> <p><strong>Working with sourdough is a combination art and science.</strong> One the one hand, most recipes are measured in grams, starters can be sensitive to the most random things, and you tend to get the most consistent results if you yourself are consistent. On the other hand, there are many bakers who go purely by consistency and vibe of the dough and their creations turn out fantastic (I stand by the fact that it’s subconscious experience on their part but whatever). What ever you do, starters are strong and surprisingly resilient! If it looks or feels like you killed it, take a little bit of starter and try to revitalize it in a new jar with daily feedings.</p> <h2 id="recipes">Recipes</h2> <p>Here are a few of my favorite sourdough recipes I’ve tried over the past year or so.</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://www.allrecipes.com/recipe/260540/chef-johns-sourdough-bread/">Chef John’s Sourdough Bread</a> The most quintessential sourdough recipe, the basic loaf. Tho many call it “basic”, I call it delicious with everything that I pair it with. It works well in a loaf pan as well as round and on a baking sheet. Just make sure you get some steam in there to get a nice crackly crust. You also don’t need to use bread flour if you don’t have it. All-purpose is fine.</li> <li><a href="https://makeitdough.com/sourdough-monkey-bread/">Sourdough Monkey Bread</a> A sweet treat with a lovely tang.</li> <li><a href="https://www.farmhouseonboone.com/pumpkin-sourdough-bread/">Pumpkin Sourdough Bread</a> Fall in bread form (especially when paired with maple butter). You don’t have to go the extra mile with the pumpkin shape, I just shape it like I do a normal loaf. Squash puree is a good substitute if you don’t want to buy canned pumpkin.</li> </ul> <p>Reach out to me if you have any and all questions, I love talking about fermentations!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="baking,"/><category term="guide"/><category term="baking,"/><category term="recipe"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a quick and dirty guide to starting sourdough projects]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Website construction process</title><link href="https://katielf.github.io/blog/2025/website-construction-process/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Website construction process"/><published>2025-03-25T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-25T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://katielf.github.io/blog/2025/website-construction-process</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://katielf.github.io/blog/2025/website-construction-process/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="check-list-for-constructing-everything">Check List for constructing everything</h4> <ul class="task-list"> <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" checked="checked"/>Remove “news” section (instructions in CUSTOMIZE)</li> <li class="task-list-item">[] Color, background? (found in _themes.scss)</li> <li class="task-list-item">[] Color, highlights (change to a green or cooler purple)(themes.scss)</li> <li class="task-list-item">[] Font, body text</li> <li class="task-list-item">[] Font, header</li> <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" checked="checked"/>Blog, remove example posts</li> <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" checked="checked"/>Blog/posts, write 2 posts</li> <li class="task-list-item">[] CV, create (everything everything or targeted?)</li> <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" checked="checked"/>Publication, “coming soon?” sign OR add to ‘exclude’ section for now?</li> <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" checked="checked"/>Home page, intro statement</li> <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" checked="checked"/>Home page, structure</li> <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" checked="checked"/>Social Media information</li> <li class="task-list-item">[] Research Lighthouse Badger (I have no need of it now)</li> <li class="task-list-item">[] Projects, add relevant categories</li> <li class="task-list-item">[] Add drop caps, somehow and someway</li> </ul> <hr/> <p>I want this website to be professional but also have a lot of personal touch and a glimpse of hobbies.</p> <blockquote> <p>If at first you don’t succeed, find out why. —Ms. Frizzle</p> </blockquote> <p>This will be my mantra as I create and customize everything. It’s a fantastic learning experience.</p> <p><em>update 4-17-25</em> I’m in a bit of a holding pattern with this website project. I want to add more content that relates to my skills as a researcher and data person but apparently I have not made many (if any) good projects to showcase that! So now I feel I need to make content before I can work on aesthetics any more…</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="update"/><category term="update"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[documentation on customizing this website]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chloe K’s Kombucha tips</title><link href="https://katielf.github.io/blog/2018/Next-Chloe-Kombucha/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chloe K’s Kombucha tips"/><published>2018-08-08T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2018-08-08T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://katielf.github.io/blog/2018/Next-Chloe-Kombucha</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://katielf.github.io/blog/2018/Next-Chloe-Kombucha/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="this-is-a-document-from-my-friend-chloe-k-about-her-kombucha-process-i-have-put-it-here-for-histories-sake-so-i-dont-loose-it">This is a document from my friend Chloe K. about her kombucha process. I have put it here for histories sake so I don’t loose it.</h4> <p>Morning! As requested, here’s a brief run-down of the kombucha process: </p> <p>Begin with 4 simple ingredients:  Tea: it needs to be an unflavored, “true tea” blend. People commonly use: english breakfast, oolong, green tea, or any blend/combination of those. While black tea is best for SCOBY health (due in part to the SCOBY feeding off the caffeine), green tea gives the best flavor.  The higher quality tea the better the base will taste and the true kombucha brewer’s flex is to bottle and serve a delicious plain kombucha. HOWEVER, if you’re ballin’ on a budget and/or like to add a lot of flavors (I’m guilty on both accounts) a simple, pre-bagged tea will be more than sufficient; for a one gallon batch I like to use between 12-14 tea bags, depending on taste and SCOBY heath (if you’re not seeing a nice opaque colorless film on top at the end of your brew you may need to up your tea).  Sugar: While my personal preferences are for organic and fair trade, chemically speaking any white sugar will do. People have experimented with other sweeteners, but the only other really successful one is honey. Honey kombucha is DELICIOUS, but brewers often steer away as it is highly costly. (Side bar: green tea base honey sweetened kombucha is called Jun and it’s often referred to as “The Champagne of Kombuchas.) As for the quantity of sugar, that will depend on: desired sweetness in final product, ambient temperature (which fluctuates seasonally), and anticipated length of brew cycle. In the winter, when ambient temperature in my house was a non-optimal 65 degrees, I was using 2.25 cups; in the summer when the brewing shelf is an opposingly non-optimal 80 degrees, I’ve been sticking with 3 cups. Either way I have it on a 7 day brewing cycle. (And while we’re talking about temperature, my optimal temp would be EXACTLY 72 degrees. I’ll stand by that number, but that’s more kombucha 202 level knowledge.) SCOBY: This is the active culture that turns that overly sweet tea into kombucha. Visually they’re not great to behold: they’re semi-opaque, tea-colored, slime patties with yeast strands hanging off the older layers. Like the rings of a tree can give indications of growing conditions for that season, each brew cycle SHOULD add another layer to the SCOBY and new growth will indicate brewing conditions; not that that’s necessary information, but it is FASCINATING! The easiest way to obtain a SCOBY is to talk to your kombucha-brewing friends, there always seems to be SCOBY to spare. If you’re out of luck, it’s actually quite simple to grow your own from store bought kombucha:  Find a totally unflavored bottle of kombucha (this will probably be the hardest part, TBH). Then dump it in the brewing container and feed it some sweet tea and come back in about 2-3 weeks. The still active cultures will have created your own SCOBY! And with the SCOBY you’ll want some tart kombucha/starter liquid to be sure the SCOBY is in a PH balanced environment that will keep it healthy.  Water: This is sorta a given, but water will be used to make the tea. No need to be fancy about this one. </p> <p>The “Simple” Process:  1. Boil water. Add sugar and tea. Remove from heat and let it steep. Let this “starter tea” cool to room temperature before adding to the SCOBY container. (You’re trying to avoid pasteurizing the SCOBY.) 2. Let sit with the SCOBY for ~7 days. Taste at regular intervals so you can become familiar with how fast the SCOBY is working and stop the fermentation when it’s just a bit sweeter than you want it.  3. Drain out kombucha liquid, leaving like 1/6 of the liquid in with the SCOBY for the next batch. Now is when you add your flavors and let it infuse for ~3 days. 1. Use really any fruit or herbs you want for flavoring. Fresh fruit works best, frozen is also quite good; crush it up a bit before adding to encourage maximum flavor transfer. Some good dried herbs to use in kombucha are: ginger, lavender, and/ or mint; if you have a favorite herbal tea, a few of those tea bags might be a good addition.  4. After 3 days, strain out chunks and bottle. This last step is just to get carbonation, so an air-tight seal is ESSENTIAL. Old kombucha bottles work great and are a very affordable option, just be SURE that they’re screwed on as tight as possible. Wire “swing tops” make you look very legit and will always get a great seal, just be sure they’re “fermentation grade”, no dinky cheap imitations, those will shatter.  5. After 7 days the bottles SHOULD be carbonated, but it’s helpful to pop one open to check. It should make a fizzing sound like opening a pop. It MAY overflow like a baking soda volcano, so if it’s been particularly warm I’d recommend opening it outside. If they’re carbonated to your satisfaction, put them in the fridge to stop fermentation. Bottles will stay good in the fridge for 2 weeks; after that they’ll still be good, but you may notice a difference in taste since they’re still fermenting, just MUCH slower. Kombucha never goes bad, it only gets funkier. </p> <p>Anyways Katie, let me know if you have any remaining questions. </p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="fermentation,"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[an update about what is going on for me career and skill wise]]></summary></entry></feed>