<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://katielf.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://katielf.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-04-10T20:16:44+00:00</updated><id>https://katielf.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Katie L. Friese</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Sourdough tips and tricks</title><link href="https://katielf.github.io/blog/2025/Sourdough-tips-and-tricks/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sourdough tips and tricks"/><published>2025-04-10T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-10T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://katielf.github.io/blog/2025/Sourdough-tips-and-tricks</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://katielf.github.io/blog/2025/Sourdough-tips-and-tricks/"><![CDATA[<p>This is for a few friends at the DANCE lab that are just getting started in their sourdough adventure and needed a few starting tips.</p> <h1 id="introduction-to-fermentation">Introduction to ~fermentation~</h1> <p>Welcome to the amazing world of fermentation! That’s right! You have a bunch of lovely bacteria and wild yeasts that will help you make fantastic sourdough bread, rolls, and treats galore.</p> <p>For a more technical definition, a sourdough starter is a leavening agent in baking. It has it’s own quirks just like regular yeast or baking soda. Because it’s technically a living thing, it tends to get more picky with what it eats and grows in. But what it does eat it turns into carbon dioxide which is the rising agent for baking.</p> <p><strong>It should be in glass most of the time</strong> (all plastic is permeable in some way or another) <strong>but should be given the ability to breath.</strong> My favorite method is to put it in a glass mason jar and secure the top with a towel and a rubber band.</p> <p>PICTURE HERE OF MY BEAUTIFUL BABY BOY STERLING</p> <p>Just like with any leaving thing you need to feed it. But, like a cat, it doesn’t need to be super consistent. If you’re not planning on using it anytime soon, feed it and pop it in the fridge for a few weeks. Starter is surprisingly resilient and will usually spring back after a few feedings outside of the fridge.</p> <p>But what should you feed this wonderful conglomerate? <strong>A typical feeding as measured in grams (oh yeah, a scale will be your best friend in sourdough baking) is 1 part flour, 1 part water, and a bit of starter.</strong> How fast it ferments depends on how much starter you add, the ambient temperature, what minerals are in your water, etc. etc.</p> <p><strong>Working with sourdough is a combination art and science.</strong> One the one hand, most recipes are measured in grams, starters can be sensitive to the most random things, and you tend to get the most consistent results if you yourself are consistent. On the other hand, there are many bakers who go purely by consistency and vibe of the dough and their creations turn out fantastic (I stand by the fact that it’s subconscious experience on their part but whatever).</p> <h2 id="recipes">Recipes</h2> <p>Here are a few of my favorite sourdough recipes I’ve tried over the past year or so.</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://www.allrecipes.com/recipe/260540/chef-johns-sourdough-bread/">Chef John’s Sourdough Bread</a> The most quintessential sourdough recipe, the basic loaf. Tho many call it “basic”, I call it delicious with everything that I pair it with. It works well in a loaf pan as well as round and on a baking sheet. Just make sure you get some steam in there to get a nice crackly crust. You also don’t need to use bread flour if you don’t have it. All-purpose is fine.</li> <li><a href="https://makeitdough.com/sourdough-monkey-bread/">Sourdough Monkey Bread</a> A sweet treat with a lovely tang.</li> <li><a href="https://www.farmhouseonboone.com/pumpkin-sourdough-bread/">Pumpkin Sourdough Bread</a> Fall in bread form (especially when paired with maple butter). You don’t have to go the extra mile with the pumpkin shape, I just shape it like I do a normal loaf. Squash puree is a good substitute if you don’t want to buy canned pumpkin.</li> </ul> <p>Reach out to me if you have any and all questions, I love talking about fermentations!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="baking,"/><category term="guide"/><category term="baking,"/><category term="recipe"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a quick and dirty guide to starting sourdough projects]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Website construction process</title><link href="https://katielf.github.io/blog/2025/website-construction-process/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Website construction process"/><published>2025-03-25T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-25T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://katielf.github.io/blog/2025/website-construction-process</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://katielf.github.io/blog/2025/website-construction-process/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="check-list-for-constructing-everything">Check List for constructing everything</h4> <ul class="task-list"> <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" checked="checked"/>Remove “news” section (instructions in CUSTOMIZE)</li> <li class="task-list-item">[] Color, background? (found in _themes.scss)</li> <li class="task-list-item">[] Color, highlights (change to a green or cooler purple)(themes.scss)</li> <li class="task-list-item">[] Font, body text</li> <li class="task-list-item">[] Font, header</li> <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" checked="checked"/>Blog, remove example posts</li> <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" checked="checked"/>Blog/posts, write 2 posts</li> <li class="task-list-item">[] CV, create (everything everything or targeted?)</li> <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" checked="checked"/>Publication, “coming soon?” sign OR add to ‘exclude’ section for now?</li> <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" checked="checked"/>Home page, intro statement</li> <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" checked="checked"/>Home page, structure</li> <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" checked="checked"/>Social Media information</li> <li class="task-list-item"><input type="checkbox" class="task-list-item-checkbox" disabled="disabled" checked="checked"/>Research Lighthouse Badger (I have no need of it now)</li> <li class="task-list-item">[] Projects, add relevant categories</li> </ul> <hr/> <p>I want this website to be professional but also have a lot of personal touch and a glimpse of hobbies.</p> <blockquote> <p>If at first you don’t succeed, find out why. —Ms. Frizzle</p> </blockquote> <p>This will be my mantra as I create and customize everything. It’s a fantastic learning experience.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="update"/><category term="update"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[documentation on customizing this website]]></summary></entry></feed>